[Music]
Reedman
reads Giver by Lois Lowry narrated by Fraser Reedman chapter
3 "Oh, look!" Lily salled in delight. "Isn't he cute? Look how tiny he is! And he has
funny eyes like yours, Jonas!" Jonas glared at her. He didn't like that she had mentioned his
eyes. He waited for his father to chastise Lily Father was busy unstrapping the
carrying basket from the back of his bicycle. Jonas walked over to
look. It was the first thing Jonas noticed as he looked at the new child
peering up curiously from the basket pale eyes. Almost every citizen in the
community had dark eyes. His parents did Lily did so did all his group members and friends
there were a few exceptions: Jonas himself, and a female Five who he had
noticed had a different, lighter eyes. No one mentioned such things; it was not a
rule, but was considered rude to call attention to things that were unsettling
or different about individuals. Lily, he decided, would have to learn that soon, or she would be
called in for chastisement because of her insensitive chatter. Father put his
bike into its port and he picked up the basket and carried it into the house.
Lily followed behind she glanced back over her shoulder at Jonas and teased,
"Maybe he had the same birth mother as you." Jonas shrugged. He followed them
inside he had been startled by the new child's eyes. Mirrors were rare in the
community; they weren't forbidden, but there was no real need of them, and Jonas
had simply never bothered to look at himself very often even when he found
himself in a location where a mirr existed.
Now, seeing the new child in its expression, he was reminded that the
light eyes were not only a rarity but gave the one who had them a certain look—
—what was it dep he decided; as if one were looking into the clear water of the
river, down to the bottom, where things might lurk which hadn't been discovered
yet. He felt self-conscious, realizing that he, too, had that look. He went to his
desk, pretending not to be interested in the new child
On the other side of the room, Mother and Lily were bending over to watch as
Father unwrapped its blanket. "What's his comfort object called?"
Lily asked, picking up the stuffed creature which had been placed beside the new child in his
basket. Father glanced at it. "Hippo," he said. Lily giggled at the strange word.
"Hippo," she repeated, and put the comfort object down again. She peered at the unwrapped child
who waved his arms.
"I think new children are so cute," Lily sighed. "I hope I get assigned to be a birth
mother Lily!" Mother spoke very sharply.
"Don't say that. There's very little honor in that Assignment I was talking to
Natasia You know the 10 who lives around the corner? She does some of her
volunteer hours at the Birthing Center.
And she told me that the birth mothers get wonderful food, and they have very
gentle exercise periods, and most of the time they just play games and amuse
themselves while they're waiting.
I think I'd like that," Lily said petulantly. "Three years," Mother told her
for Three births, and that's all. After that they are Laborers for the rest of
their adult lives, until the day they enter the House of Old. Is that what you
want, Lily? Three lazy years, and then hard physical labor until you were
old?" "Well, no, I guess not," Lily acknowledged reluctantly. Father turned the new child
onto his tummy in the basket. He sat beside it and rubbed its small back with a rhythmic
motion. "Anyway ly Billy he said affectionately, "the birth mothers never
even get to see the new children If you enjoy the little ones so much, you should
hope for an Assignment as a
Nurturer." "When you're an Eight and start your volunteer hours, you can try some at
the Nurturing Center," Mother suggested. "Yes, I think I will," Lily said.
She she knelt beside the basket. "What did you say his name is?
Gabriel? Hello, Gabriel," she said in a sing song voice and Then she
giggled oops she whispered. "I think he's asleep. I guess I better be
quiet Jon has turned to the school assignments on his desk. Some chance of
that, he thought but he was never quiet. Probably she should hope for an
Assignment as Speaker, so she could sit in the office with a microphone all they
making an announcement He laughed silently to himself, picturing his sister
droning on in the self-important voice that all the Speakers seemed to develop, saying things
like, ATTENTION, THIS IS A REMINDER TO FEMALES UNDER NINE THAT HAIR RIBBONS ARE
NEATLY TIED AT ALL TIMES. He turned toward Lily and noticed to his satisfaction that her ribbons
were, as usual, undone and dangling be an announcement like that
quite soon, he felt certaint and it would be directed mainly at Lily her name, of
course, would not be mentioned. Everyone would know. Everyone had known, he
remembered with humiliation, that the announcement ATTENTION, THIS IS A
REMINDER TO MALE Els THAT OBJECTS ARE NOT TO BE REMOVED FROM THE RECREATION
AREA AND THAT SNACKS ARE TO BE EATEN, NOT HOARDED had been specifically directed
at him, the day last month that he had taken an apple
home. No one had mentioned it, not even his parents, because the public
announcement had been sufficient to produce the appropriate remorse. He had,
of course dispose of the apple and made his apology to the Recreation Director
the next morning, before school. Jonas thought again about that
incident. He was still bewildered by it.
Not by the announcement or the necessary apology; those were standard procedures,
and he had deserved them by the incident itself. He probably should have brought
up his feeling of bewilderment that very evening when the family unit had shared
their feelings of the day he had not been able to sort out and put words to
the source of his confusion, so he' let it pass. It had happened during the
recreation period, when he had been playing with Asher. Jonas had casually picked up an
apple from the basket where the snacks were kept, and had thrown it to his
friend. Asher had thrown it back, and they had begun a simple game of
catch. There had been nothing special about it was an activity that he
performed countless times: throw, catch; throw, catch. It was effortless for Jonas,
and even boring, though Asher enjoyed it, and playing catch was a required
activity for Asher because it would improve his hand ey coordination, which was not up to
standards suddenly Jonas had noticed, following the path of the apple through
the air with his eyes the piece of fruit had— —well, this was the part that he
couldn't adequately understand— —the apple had changed. Just for an
instant. It had changed in midair he remembered and it was in his hand, and he
looked at it carefully, but it was the same apple.
Unchanged same size and shape perfect sphere. The same nondescript shade, about
the same shade as his own tunic. There was absolutely nothing remarkable about
that apple. He had tossed it back and forth between his hands a few times and
thrown it again to Asher. And again— —in the air, for an instant only— —it had
changed. It had happened four times. Jonas had blinked, looked around,
and then tested his eyesight, squinting at the small print on the identification
badge attached to his tunic. He read his name quite clearly. He
could also see Asher at the other end of the throwing area he had had no problem
catching the apple. Jonas had been completely mystified. "Ash?" he had called. "Does
anything seem strange to you? About the apple?" "Yes," Asher called back, laughing. "It
jumps out of my hand onto the ground!"
Asher had just dropped it once again. So Jonas laughed too, and with his
laughter tried to ignore his uneasy conviction that something had
happened he had taken the apple home, against the recreation area
rules. That evening, before his parents and Lily arrived at the dwelling, he held
it in his hands and looked at it carefully. It was slightly bruised now as
Asher dropped it several times there was nothing at all unusual about the
app He had held a magnifying glass to it.
He had tossed it several times across the room, watching, and then rolled around
and around on his desktop, waiting for the thing to happen again. But it hadn't.
The only thing that happened was the announcement later that evening over the
speaker, the announcement that had singled him out without using his name
it caused both of his parents to glance meaningfully at the desk where the apple
still lay sitting at his desk, staring at his schoolwork as his family hovered
over the new child in its basket, he shook his head, trying to
forget the odd incident. He forced himself to arrange his papers and to try
to study a little bit before the evening meal. The new child Gabriel, stirred and
whimpered, and Father spoke softly to Lily, explaining the feeding procedure as
he opened the container that held the formula and equipment. The evening
proceeded as all evenings did in the family unit, in the dwelling, in the
community: quiet, reflective, a time for renewal and preparation for the day to
come was different only in the addition to it of the new chop with his pale,
solemn, knowing eyes
[Music]